Jobs are going to be replaced by AI.
It's growing in healthare two times
faster in healthcare than any other
industry. It comes down to one single
word, trust, the focus on the future
[music] 2026. So we're going to start
the series on April 15th with digital
health. [music] Then we're going to move
to AI and healthcare and yours truly,
Chris, is going to be the lead speaker
for our April 29th event. Then we're
going to move to coding and
classification and terminologies [music]
on May 13th. And then we're going to
close it out on May 27th talking about
leadership and workforce development. Go
to ifmaima.org and you'll on our
homepage you can sign up and decide what
ticket might work best for you.
Lorraine, it has been a while and it's
so good to see you. I'm really excited
to welcome you to the Sigma Room
podcast.
Well, thanks Chris. It certainly has
been a while,
right? I I don't I don't even remember.
It's been a long time. And then recently
we reconnected again. And it's, you
know, the things that we thought were a
big deal way back then. Turns out we're
insignificant compared to what we're
dealing with today. So really excited to
to hear from you what what your
experiences are. And of course, you've
been playing a really important role in
Athe, you know, led it through uh some
incredible years. And now it's
transitioning again. We're at a
wonderful time of the year. There's some
events coming up for we get to talk
about today, but I am thrilled to have
you. So again, welcome to the Signal
Room.
Well, thank you much, Chris. I
appreciate the invite.
So, let's just jump in. Uh kind of
alluded to the things that are much
different than they they were not so
long ago. Let's talk about the role of
of health information management and
then how is it really changed over the
last decade? I mean, there's I'm sure
there's tons, but there's probably some
significant things that you can you can
hit that probably will jar people's
memory that maybe they've forgotten
about.
Well, and that's certainly true. And as
I was thinking about what I would share
with you and and your listeners, I'll
probably reflect a little bit more than
a decade since I have a 50-year career.
I can't believe it. Uh, and
you started at 10 years old, just like
me.
I did. I did. I started at 10. and I'll
reflect some of my thoughts are on my 12
years on the ifa board also. So I'll
share a little insight and and I'm sure
this is going to spark further
conversation. So in my career I always
had a passion for data but honestly I
don't think I'm unique in that regard. I
managed people in the quote unquote
traditional health information
management department. I also managed uh
almost from day one in my career, you
know, the cancer registry or tumor
registry as it was called, trauma
registries and other types of clinical
registries cuz I just love data and any
how to capture it, how to make sure it
was accurate and my staff I I was lucky
the first 10 years of my career I found
staff who shared my passion,
right? So you fast forward a bit and you
say okay so we've evolved from paper
early in my career to electronic for
many reasons and obviously we know the
US government did a significant
investment in that from like what was it
2008 to 12 something like that. So paper
in the US is largely gone except for
perhaps some specialty areas of health
care, maybe some specialty clinics or
other niches, but you know we still have
shadow records in electronics just like
we did in paper. But the transition over
the last 15 years I believe has created
tremendous opportunity for health
information or health information
management professionals because as a
result of the infusion in the US from
the federal government to move to
electronic or to digital professionals
had a chance to lead design and
implementation teams maybe for the
products that were implemented in their
respective departments. and from that go
even bigger to leading larger teams who
are more generic to functions I'd say in
the health care system and I think that
was a fabulous springboard for the
profession to go bigger to go better to
go broader whatever else you want to add
there and I think that created the
environment where health information
professionals instead of just creating
the data as we did from release of
information or clinical coding or other
administrative functions, registration,
patient access. Um, we became users and
curators of the data. A much different
hat I think we put on as a result of
that infusion. You know, we use data in
our data analyst roles, perhaps in
information or data governance, clinical
decision support, maybe clinical
documentation improvement, and it goes
on a long ways. In particular, I'd say
the clinical coders uh are evolving now
to address clinical coding in the US and
especially around the world beyond ICD
or CPT. I I talked to global colleagues
who are working in SNOMED and in ICD
and we'll talk about those in just a
second and other clinical
classifications. Some come out of WH,
some come out of other uh regulatory or
professional associations. So I think
this has broadened our remmit to
encompass a lot more components and I
think others would agree it's the whole
of the revenue cycle management. Now,
not everybody is doing it as you and I
know and our listeners know, right?
But there's a lot of people who've moved
beyond just that one little component of
revenue cycle to manage the sides of
each of our traditional and much bigger.
And I think with that what we've seen is
we've become stewards of data as opposed
to users or curators or the creators of
data. Right? And that's stewards through
governance, through compliance, through
privacy and uh advocacy in a latter
areas. So at ifa what we did and we've
become connectors in in ifa's belief
we're the connectors that work far
beyond the data experts. were the
bridges, you could say, to knowledge and
experience and skills that are really
needed today between technical,
clinical, and administrative functions.
that that's such an important part of
what we're we're talking about today is
there's this whole function I I think
about you know from the years that I was
working in the data and analytics space
in a chief data officer role or you know
really working with multiple different
kinds of data sources because there's a
proliferation at a pace that is
staggering honestly I think the the
amount of data in all recorded history
it like not even five years ago I was
hearing it was that was happening inside
of it 2 years. Yeah.
I can't even imagine what that is like
now. It's probably 2 weeks. It It's just
staggering. But the the piece that uh
really changed the way that I had to
operate was moving from report
generation, cataloging, you know,
auditing to translation. And really what
you're talking about in this stewardship
arena is there is so much information
that's coming in with many more more
kinds of data and the timing of it is is
different. Uh the relevancy based on a
variety of factors uh is not easily
discerned. So you I think the the role
that you know these professionals that
are involved with health information
management are becoming much more
important and essential to uh our
success as we start to implement even
more I'll call it disruption I think
improvement but I think it's you know
it's more disruption at least for now it
is anyway but I think it would be really
good you know to hear your perspective
on not only is it more important but why
stewardship matters uh more as we're
moving into these these AI assisted
workflows. I mean it it's a gamecher for
sure, but the risks are significant
especially if we don't understand
stewardship and and who's responsible
and how do we lean in and do it well.
I think it comes down to one single word
trust. We must build trust from creation
and analysis to output to downstream
systems consuming it. And those
consuming systems are obviously whether
it's the workflow for the consuming
systems or the system itself heavily
using AI. If they're not today, give it
a few weeks or months and they will be.
And so without trust and and the
discussion of trust isn't brand new in
the context of AI. We've been discussing
trust for years, but I think without
trust, it's part of stewardship. We're
not going to achieve the goals that
we're talking about from automation,
digital health, AI initiatives, and the
monies that are being spent, which are
staggering, as you know, even more so
than me. um we're not going to recoup
all those rewards or all those benefits.
And I did like you uh yesterday I did a
quick query and said how much are we
really spending in AI today? And here's
what I found. 38 to 39 billion were
predicted to be spent last year right
in AI and 50 billion by the end of this
year. And that's Fortune magazine. So
it's not my opinion or your opinion.
This is some thinker out there and
researcher who's saying that and it's
growing in healthare at two times and
maybe you knew this Chris two times
faster in healthcare than any other
industry. mind-boggling.
Yeah. So I think beyond that
you know what's even more disturbing I
think in that vein is that there all the
things that were concerned about the
nefarious actors doing using this
technology they're even ahead of that
and it's just for me that's just another
reason that we have to double down now
make sure that everyone understands how
things are being used make sure we have
the the structure around it to actually
protect health care as it as the place
where you can go there still knowing
that there's people that are are there
for you and to take care of you. It's
not about you're you're not a number.
You mean you're you're a human being and
we're going to wrap the services around
your care to ensure that we preserve
that.
And and as we've hinted at, stewardship
and trust are essential. They should be
foundational to building the consumer
conference confidence as a result of AI
being a part of clinical decision making
and clinical interactions to decision
support to financial workflows. And so
advocacy becomes a big part of that
building trust now because it's every
aspect of consumer confidence, consumer
engagement with their care in order to
improve health care because we're not
doing this just to have some fun new
project to do. We want to improve health
and health outcomes.
100%. as we're thinking about this, you
know, the you mentioned governance and
it people have varying um degrees of
understanding of what that really is
about and you know probably more more of
us than not have had experiences with it
and it seems like it was been treated as
an academic exercise that is really not
what we're talking about. Um so as
you're thinking about how the the role
of HIM is expanding in the governance
quality and compliance space this is way
beyond buzzwords which for some people
it's a people it's a buzzword these are
really significant areas of
responsibility that are really really
essential. Can you talk a little bit
about how the role is expanding and what
what that really means for for him
professionals and and where they can be
and they need to be, you know, educating
themselves and stepping into higher
levels of proficiency in these areas.
Sure. And and I think I' I'd ground my
response from health information
management professionals around the
globe that I talk with week after week,
month after month because everybody
around the globe in my profession is
talking about how their role is evolving
and everybody talks about their concerns
about AI and what it's going to do to
their role, their responsibilities, how
they're going to integrate it to
workflow or how they're not going to
integrate it because of their concerns
that governance isn't adequately
addressed as as a foundational element.
And so what we did at if HEA is because
we were hearing this so much from our
professionals and it didn't matter
whether you were in the US or Canada or
Nigeria or Australia or Spain around the
globe, people are concerned. So, we
developed a toolkit that we released in
November of last year. If you go to
ifphema.org, you'll see the toolkit
there. And it's got a white paper about
the value and the adaptability of the
health information management
professional to help in digital health,
to help in privacy and security. And
last but certainly not least, the
critical role we should play in AI
design and adoption and implementation.
So I have to thank all of my colleagues.
There was about 10 of them I believe
from around the world who helped develop
this toolkit from Barbados to Iran. Yes,
we had Iranians as a part of this
despite what's going on in the world
today. to Kenya to Spain and Australia.
Everybody had good input about where's
the profession at in their country
today. Where are they struggling and why
and then what they must do to embrace
the future and prepare themselves and
their associations for the future. So
obviously the goal of all of this was
give tools to our members and we've
gotten fabulous response and I am not
exaggerating fabulous response about yes
this is what I need to go to talk to the
minister of health of why I must be a
part of this government initiative or
why I need to be involved when we're
discussing ICD-11 implementation if
they're already on whatever version of
ICD-10 they're on and it's it's impacting
the payers the providers in the US terms
we use here it's impacting all elements
of government once you kind of leave the
US it's government plays a very big role
so life is changing that's for sure
for yeah no question about that and I
think it's really really helpful to to
hear you perspectives in in the the way
that a female is is supporting this
on a global level because you know we
hear tons about what's going on here in
the US and there's all these you know
challenging things about how things are
going to get regulated where they're
going to get regulated but people are
still needing to get healthcare
everywhere and they're not waiting for
everybody to figure out the policy
stuff. So the role that Ephimma plays is
an incredibly important one. And I mean
it heartens me to know just how much uh
the organization has been doing to
support healthcare professionals around
the world. And you know we're we're all
first of all first and foremost we're
all human beings regardless of whatever
else is going on. And it's really a
wonderful thing that a FEMA is doing to
make sure that, you know, healthcare
information management teams and
professionals are keeping their eye on
the ball and they're they're really
doing a great job in moving things
forward. Um maybe can kind of pivot. Uh
I I want to get a little bit from you in
terms of you think things are going and
I think that naturally leads us into the
the invitation for people to you know
get get involved and uh with some of the
wonderful resources that are going to be
available in the coming weeks and
months. Uh we'll we'll talk about that a
little bit as well. Uh but so let's talk
about how health information management
is changing you know as the landscape is
becoming more digital and you know AI is
doing more to shape documentation and
decision support. I think recently, and
I'm sure you've have thoughts about this
too, but the the introduction of open AI
and anthropics offerings into the direct
connection with a patient with AI uh
poses some interesting scenarios to
figure out where you're dealing with AI
generated data sets that are coming in
for the electronic records.
Yes, it is. You know, as as you know,
digital health is one of the four topic
areas we're going to cover in our
four-part series. digital health in the
context of what we're discussing right
now. When we wrote this toolkit and
released it, we noted that 540 billion
is expected to be spent by 2035.
And interestingly, the World Health
Organization is firmly behind this. So
it's not the private sector, it's not
the vendors, it's not just the
healthcare delivery organizations, it is
um government and global organizations
like WH. So in that context, HIM can be
the connector to the many facets of
digital health uh expenditures,
deployments and obviously AI, artificial
intelligence. But one of the things I
have to do is is as as the marketing and
communications executive for Epheima is
remember that the HIM role varies
considerably around the globe. great
deal of variation and some many
organizations or many countries are
still struggling with how to define the
role and how to gain the recognition and
the compensation for the role that has
changed and is essential to AI and
digital health and the other things. So
at IFHIMA, we talk about how do we help
people, how do we help our members deal
with outdated job codes or labor
classification codes and that goes from
global to country specific because that
certainly does hold professionals back
in many countries. And then in other
countries that we work with, it's the
lack of formal HI or HIM programs in
their countries and the degrees that are
granted and then the lack of
credentials. So credentials and academic
programs aren't an issue or the lack of
them isn't an issue in the US. But what
you hear from people like me in the US
is, yeah, I can get a degree and I can
maintain my credentials, but I got to
make sure my job compensation
helps reward me for making that
investment and that investment helps you
and I as health care consumers. So, it's
a piggy. That's something I don't think
people realize how significant, you
know, that that investment needs to be
to to really keep up with the the the
ever evolving landscape that we're
talking about, you know, the
proliferation of data again. And not
only that, the kind of data we used
we're used to, but there's new kinds of
it that are being introduced all the
time, too.
Yeah. So I think AI it can open many
doors for health information
professionals. We've got to step forward
a few steps. We've got to take a few
risks. And that's not easy for everybody
based upon where you live, where you're
at in your career, etc. And we've got to
upskill a bit to demonstrate that we
have that broad skill set. We've got the
knowledge. We are the bridges and the
connectors that are out there. I firmly
believe that who better than us to be
the stewards of the data that we've
created historically and that we are now
using in so many different ways as a
result of how AI is is going to
revolutionize the healthcare industry
and perhaps in some facets already has.
So um great opportunities but we need to
wisely understand the data limitations
that the health information management
professional is certainly in a good
position to explain. Yeah, it's it's a
in a moment where people are concerned,
you know, if their jobs are going to be
replaced by AI and this at this point,
you've heard this before, but people's
jobs that'll be replaced will be
replaced by people who are using AI. And
you know, this is the moment if you
haven't already started as a
professional to start to figure out how
how you can use it. Now's the time to do
that. and which kind of leads very
nicely into the work that you've you've
been doing that's kind of culminating in
this next series that that Athe is is
sponsoring and the events that are
coming in and you know very very soon.
Uh love love to have you talk a little
bit about what you guys have planned and
what folks can get involved in over the
next weeks and months to to really start
to you know make some own progress make
some of their own progress in uh moving
towards being able to meet the demands
of what what's going to be required
moving forward in in the roles of uh
leaders that are involved in healthcare.
And we actually started this journey
about almost 2 years ago now because
with any event you know there there's a
good ramp of 6 to9 months at least
before you have production. So in 2025
we launched the focus on the future
series and that's why you see some of my
gray hair here. That series, it was
phenomenally accepted much broader than
what we thought it would be in all
honesty because people have a thirst for
how do I prepare for my future? If I'm
an educator, how do I prepare my
students? If I'm a professional, how do
I make sure I've got the latest
knowledge? So based upon the response in
2025, then late last year we started
planning the focus on the future 2026.
So we're going to start the series on
April 15th with digital health. Then
we're going to move to AI and healthc
care and yours truly Chris is going to
be the lead speaker for our April 29th
event. Then we're going to move to
coding and classification and
terminologies on May 13th. And then
we're going to close it out on May 27th
talking about leadership and workforce
development. It's a broad agenda. We're
going to cover two hours each. You can
attend live or you can listen on demand.
So it's really planned for the global
audience. And that's why we have to have
on demand because 6 a.m. might not work
for you in the US or in Australia or
whatever.
Right?
So we'll go from April 15th in digital
health and I'm really excited that Dr.
Osama El Hassan. And for any of your
listeners who have ever heard him talk
or read about his achievements, he has
moved mountains in the Middle East. You
know, one of the co-founders of Zean and
his organization in Abu Dhabi as well as
the UAE and the whole Middle East doing
great things. So, I know he's going to
have success stories to share and I'm
sure lessons learned and a few nuggets.
And then we're going to go to April
29th. Good. I I hope you can join us.
So, then we're going to go to April 29th
where Chris, you're going to lead us off
and we're going to talk, I believe,
about AI from many different
perspectives, governance, privacy,
consent, risk mitigation, and are there
a few other kernels you want to share?
There definitely will be some uh
probably more than I even realize now
because things are evolving so fast. But
you know, I would stay tuned. I'm sure
I'll be learning some things at the same
time.
Yeah, that's probably the truth. So then
we're going to move to May 13th, what
some people might say is is the bread
and butter, so to speak, of the health
information management profession. And
we're going to talk about coding and
classifications
and particularly about mapping across
systems because there's a lot of work
happening there. So we're going to talk
about ICD-11. Now probably in your
lifetime and mine certainly in mine
we're not going to see ICD-11 in the US.
We're going to be latent to doctor. We
all know that. But we've got to
understand what's coming because in the
decades ahead when ICD-11 comes, we're
going to use ICD-10 and the insights we
can gain from that. So we're also going
to talk about SnowMed and one of the
speakers is going to talk about the
mappings that are happening between
SnowMed and WH. That's one I'm really
interested because I I at this point
don't know a whole lot about it. And and
then we're going to have a little
conversation about other systems like
ICF and itchy that come from WH not used
much in the US. So the classifications
and functionality
or the health interventions and itchy
has come a long ways in the last few
years. So we're to talk about procedures
or interventions tied to diagnosis. So
May 13th for people who live and breathe
coding and classifications.
It's a global audience of speakers that
I've heard some of them several times
and they are just enlightening beyond
words in what they share. It's happening
out there. So then last but not least,
we're going to go to May 27th where Dr.
Christy Lamach who has just retired as a
professor from the University of Alabama
in Birmingham. She's now uh SVP at the
Scottsdale Institute and she's going to
talk about leadership and workforce
development that's needed for the
future. So, uh I've heard great things
about her. I've not heard her speak, but
she comes highly, highly recommended.
And we've got a nice list of global
speakers that will round out. And then
in all of these, I should add, there are
panel discussions. And that was the
number one thing our attendees told us
last year. Please give your panels more
time because the discussion amongst the
panelists because first they're going to
react to what the speakers ahead of them
said, but then they're going to discuss
perhaps inconsistencies across that
differing viewpoints a and arrive at
probably some pretty uh common
denominators that the audiences really
liked. And the best part of it perhaps
is the audience gets to ask questions.
So, there's going to be a chat feature
and a Q&A. So, get ready, Chris, because
what's going to come from the Q&A
sometimes is a bit surprising. So, it's
going to be very interactive if you can
listen and participate in the live
event. And even if you have to listen to
it on demand, you're going to hear what
everybody thinks and feels as a part of
the panel discussions.
This is exciting. that you you talked
about the the the focus on career
development and and the the directions
that people have to go in their career
that the equipping that's required here.
I'm that I'm I'm super excited to hear
about that because no matter what you're
doing, if you're working inside of any
organization, these are things that
people are concerned about. So I these
sessions are incredible. I I'm very
excited and people
if you haven't already made made a
decision to to sign on to sign up for
these I encourage you go to the website
of fema.org definitely sign sign up for
these things. Um we're going to put a
bunch of information in the show notes
for for folks as well. Want to make it
really easy for you to find your find
your way. U make sure you're telling all
your friends and colleagues. Um this is
a really important moment in time and a
FEMA has done incredible work uh to put
this or all these programs together to
equip you for what you're about to
embark on and we've not seen anything
yet. So definitely take advantage of all
these opportunities. it it's really this
is the time um to absorb everything you
possibly can and start leading your
organizations with uh great equipping
and the the knowledge that you'll need
uh to to really guide and lead your your
organizations and your efforts in the
HIM space uh in the months and years to
come. And thanks and and I think I'd
close my thoughts with we want to ensure
that our members and we're going to have
a lot of non-members that are going to
come to these events and this series. We
want them to have the tools to thrive
and that is part of Epheima's mission to
ensure we enable our membership to
thrive and that includes our national
association. So whether it's Aheima, the
Chima from Canada, HIMA from Australia,
and roughly [clears throat] 20 other
nations that are a part of our
membership, we want to make sure all of
your listeners and all of the
professionals around the world have the
tools to thrive into the future because
it's not just important to their
personal careers. It's important to you
and I. I firmly believe as healthcare
consumers, we're going to do better if
we have better data that is better
stewarded that we have more trust in
because from that we're going to have
better health and better health outcomes
and that is exactly what we're all
motivated by. I believe if you're
involved in this space that's what makes
you tick. So good on FEMA for really
taking taking the the lead in this and
know good on you Lorraine and incoming
leadership of Lynette. You all are
amazing and I I couldn't be more excited
to to be able to you know provide a
platform to get the word out and I'm
blown away and and humbled by the the
invitation to be part of the the event
in at the end of April. Uh very much
looking forward to it. you all doing far
more important work than most people
realize. Um,
but it needs to be it really needs to be
elevated and I'm very excited for more
people to hear about it and between your
network and my network and a few other
people's networks, we should be able to
get the word out pretty well and improve
the the reach of the organization and
equip and help more people to to thrive
as they're going through this this
transformation that we're facing ahead
of us.
So, thanks. We we appreciate it. So go
to ifmaimma.org and you'll on our
homepage you can sign up and decide what
ticket might work best for you.
Fantastic. Lorine is always it's been
been a really fun conversation. I always
learn things when I talk to you. Uh and
I always get more excited because you're
so passionate about what you do and
you're the right person for for the work
that has been done and what you've done
has has been extraordinary. Um, so we'll
still let a few more people get inspired
by you. We'll just spread the good cheer
all the way around here. I I just love
the the infectious passion that you have
and can't thank you enough and it it's
it's absolutely an honor. So, thank you
so much for joining me on the singer
room and can't wait to be working
together with you over the next few
weeks.
Great. See you soon.
We actually started this journey about
almost two years ago now in 2025 we
[music] launched the focus on the future
series. It was phenomenally accepted
based upon the response in [music] 2025.
We started planning the focus on the
future 2026. We're going to start the
series on April 15th with digital
health. Then we're going to move to AI
and healthcare and [music] yours truly
Chris is going to be the lead speaker
for our April 29th event. Then we're
going to move to coding and
classification and terminologies on May
13th. And then we're going to close it
out on May 27th talking about leadership
and workforce development. You can
attend live or you can listen on demand.
So it's really planned for the global
audience. Go to ifa.org [music] and
you'll on our homepage you can sign up
and decide what ticket might work best
for you.